Good morning, I am Shudeshna Sharkha. Today, we start the first lecture on machine learning.
This is module 1, part a. Today, we will introduce machine learning, go through the basics of
the course, discuss the brief history of machine learning and discuss what learning
is about and some simple applications of machine learning.
So, first this is the overview of the course. The course is over 8 weeks and we will have
8 modules. The first module is introduction. In the second module, we will discuss about
linear regression and decision trees. Third module, instance-based learning and feature
selection. Fourth module, probability and base learning. Fifth module, support vector
machines. Sixth module, neural networks. Seventh module, we will do an introduction to
computational learning theory and possibly a little bit of ensemble learning. And then
the last module, we will talk about clustering. In the first module, that is introduction,
we will have four parts. Today, we will give a brief introduction. In the next lecture,
we will have discuss about different types of learning, supervised, unsupervised, etcetera.
Then, we will have the third module, where we will talk about hypothesis space and inductive
bias. Following this, we will talk about evaluation, training and test set and cross
validation. First, I will like to start with a brief history of machine learning. A machine
that is intellectually capable as much as humans has always fired the imagination of
writers and also the early computer scientists, who were excited about artificial intelligence
and machine learning. But the first machine learning system was developed in the 1950s.
In 1952, Arthur Samuel, who was at IBM, he developed a program for playing checkers.
The program was able to observe positions at the game and learn a model that gives better
moves for the machine player. The system played many games with the program and observed that
the program was able to play better in the course of time with getting more experience
of board games. Samuel coined the term machine learning and he defined learning as a field
of study that gives computers the ability without being explicitly programmed. In 1957,
Rosenblatt proposed the perceptron. Perceptron is the simple neural network unit. It was
a very exciting discovery at that time. Rosenblatt made the following statement. The perceptron
is designed to illustrate some of the fundamental properties of intelligent systems in general
without becoming too deeply enmeshed in the special and frequently unknown conditions
which hold for particular biological organisms. But after three years, Widrow and Hoff came up
with the delta learning rule that is used for learning perceptrons. It was used as
a procedure for training perceptron. It is also known as the least square problem.
The combination of these ideas created a good linear classifier. However, the work along this line
suffered a setback when Minsky in 1969 came up with the limitations of perceptron. He
showed that the XOR problem could not be represented by perceptron and such inseparable data
distributions cannot be handled. And following this Minsky's work, Burel Network Research
went dormant up until the 1980s. In the meantime, in the 1970s, machine learning
followed the symbolic type of artificial intelligence, good old fashioned artificial intelligence.
Those types of learning algorithms were developed. Concept induction was worked on and then J. R.
Quinlan in 1986 came up with decision tree learning specifically the ID-3 algorithm. It
was also released as a software and it had simplistic rules contrary to the black box
of neural networks and it became quite popular. After ID-3, many alternatives or improvement
to ID-3 were developed such as cart, regression trees and it is still one of the very popular
topics in machine learning. During this time, symbolic natural language processing also
became very popular. In 1980s, advanced decision trees and rule learning were developed.
Learning, planning, problem solving was there. At the same time, there was a resurgence of
neural network. The intuition of multi-layer perceptron was suggested by Wehrbos in 1981
and neural network specific back propagation algorithm was developed. Back propagation
is the key ingredient of today's neural network architectures. With those ideas,
neural network research became popular again and there was an acceleration in 1985-86 when
neural network researchers presented the idea of MLP that is multi-layer perceptron with
practical BP training, Rumelhardt, Hinton, Williams, H. Nielsen, where some of the
scientists who worked in this area. During this time, theoretical framework of machine
learning was also presented, the Allianz-Pak learning theory which stands for probably approximately
correct learning it was developed and the focus shifted on experimental methodologies.
In the 90s, machine learning embraced statistics to a large extent. It was during this time
that support vector machines were proposed. It was a machine learning breakthrough and
the support vector machines were proposed by Wapnick and Cortes in 1995 and SVM had very
strong theoretical standing and empirical results.
Then another strong machine learning model was proposed by Freund and Schappeyer in 1997
which was part of what we called ensembles or boosting and they came up with a algorithm
called Adaboost by which they could create a strong classifier from an ensemble of weak
classifiers. The kernelized version of SVM was proposed near 2000s which was able to
exploit the knowledge of convex optimization, generalization and kernels. Another ensemble
model was explored by Breiman in 2001 that ensembles multiple decision trees where each
of them is curated by a random subset of instances. This is called random forest. During this
time base net learning was also proposed. Then a neural network took another damage
by the work of Hawkriter. Hawkriter showed that gradient loss after the saturation
of neural network unit happens when we apply back propagation so that after a certain
number of epochs neural networks are inclined to overfit. But as we come closer today we see
that neural networks are again very much popular. We have a new era in neural network called
deep learning and this phrase refers to neural network with many deep layers. This
is the conjunction of many different discoveries by people like Hinton, Lecun, Benjio, Andrew
NG and other researchers. At the same time if you look at certain applications where machine
learning has come to the public forefront in 1994 the first self-driving car made a road
test. In 1997 Deep Blue beat the world champion Garry Kasparov in the game of chess. In 2009
we have Google building self-driving cars. In 2011 Watson again from IBM won the popular
game of Geoparty. 2014 we see human visions are passed by ML systems. In 2014-15 we
find that machine translation systems driven by neural networks are very good and they
are better than the other statistical machine translation systems. There are certain concepts
and certain technology which are making headlines. Now in machine learning we have GPUs which
are enabling the use of machine learning and deep neural networks. There is the cloud, there
is availability of big data and the field of machine learning is very exciting now.
So, with this brief introduction of machine learning history we will now discuss what is
machine learning? What is a learning algorithm? First let us look at how a machine learning
solution differs from a programmatic solution. When you have a program or an algorithm to
solve a problem this is how you use the computer. This is your computer and you
write a program. The program takes data as the input and the program produces output.
On the other hand when you are using machine learning and you have the computer you are
feeding the data input as well as examples of output. So, you are putting examples of
input output data and you are getting a program or a model with which you can solve subsequent
tasks. So, this is what learning is about. So, with this let us come to the formal
definition of machine learning. Learning is the ability to improve one's behavior
with experience. So, it is about building computer systems that automatically improve with experience
and we have to discuss what are the fundamental laws that govern the learning processes.
Machine learning explores algorithms that learn from data, build models from data
and this model can be used for different tasks. For example, model can be used for prediction,
decision making or solving tasks. We will discuss a formal definition of machine learning
as given by Tom Mitchell and this is a definition that is followed very popularly. So, Mitchell's
it says that a computer program is said to learn, what does it learn from? It learns from
experience. So, the computer program learns from experience E. So, E is the experience
of the computer program users. It is past data with respect to some class of tasks
T, performance measured P. It is performance on tasks in T, on tasks in T as measured by
P improves with experience E. So, learning is about using experience data that is from
past problem solving data and there is a task, the task belongs to a class of tasks
T and the tasks are evaluated by performance measured P and the machine is said to learn
tasks in T if its performance at tasks as measured by P improves with experience E. So,
what we see is that the components of a learning algorithm are follows is the behavior
of the task behavior or the task that the learning program is seeking to improve. For
example, there are different types of tasks like prediction, classification, acting in
an environment etcetera. The second component is the data or the experience. So, the
experience is also called the data. This is what is used for improving the experience of
the task and then there is a measure of improvement P. For example, you might want to increase
accuracy in prediction or you might want to have new skills to the agent which it
did not earlier process or improve efficiency of problem solving corresponding to this
you can define the performance measure. So, based on this definition we can look at a learning
system as a box. So, this is our learning system it is a box to which we feed the
experience or the data and there is a problem or a problem or a problem or a problem
a task that requires solution and you can also give background knowledge which will help
the system and for this problem or this task the learning program comes up with an answer
or a solution and it is corresponding performance can be measured. So, this is the schematic
diagram of a machine learning system or a learner system. Inside there are two components two
main components the learner L and the reasoner. See the learner takes the experience and from
that it can also take the background knowledge and from this the learner builds models and
this models can be used by the reasoner which given a task finds the solution to the task.
So, the learner takes experience and background knowledge and learns a model and the reasoner
works with the model and given a new problem or task it can come up with the solution
to the task and the performance measure corresponding to this. Now, we will like to look at some examples
of machine learning system. So, machine learning there are many domains and applications of
machine learning. For example, in medicine you can use machine learning to diagnose
a disease where the input are the symptoms, lab measurements, test results, DNA tests
etcetera. Output could be one of a set of possible diseases or none of them. For doing this one
can data mine historical medical records and learn which future patients will respond
best to which treatments. Another domain is computer vision where given an image you
want to find out what objects appear in an image and where the objects appear in an image.
A third domain robot control one can use machine learning to design autonomous mobile robots
that learn to navigate from their own experience. Then in the domain of natural language processing
one can detect where entities are mentioned in natural language and detect what facts are
expressed in natural language. One can look at a product or movie review and find out
if it is positive, negative or neutral that is the sentiment on the review. Other applications
in NLP include speech recognition, machine translation etcetera. In the financial domain one can try
to predict if a stock will rise or fall. One can predict if a user will click on an advertisement
or not. There are many applications in business intelligence. You want to robustly forecast
product sales quantities, taking seasonality and trend into account, identify cross selling
promotional opportunities, identify price sensitivity of a consumer product, optimize product location
at a supermarket shelf and so on. Then there are other applications such as fraud detection,
credit card fraud detection, understand consumer sentiment, forecast women's conviction rates
based on external macroeconomic factors etcetera. So, these are some of the many many applications
of machine learning. Machine learning is a part of many products and systems that
we routinely use. If you look at the box that we drew for machine learning systems
and discuss how we can go about creating a learner these are the following steps. First
of all we choose the training experience or the training data. Then we choose the target
function or how we want to represent the model. So, this is what we want to learn the target
function that is to be learned. For example, if you are trying to write a machine learning
system to play the game of checkers the target function would be given a board position what
move to take and then we want to have the class of function that we will use. The task
is given a board position what move to take and we will design the function as a function
of the input and we have to decide what type of function we will use whether we will use
a linear function or some other representation. So, we choose how to represent the target function
and finally, we choose a learning algorithm to infer the target function. So, the learning
algorithm will explore the possible function parameters so that based on the training experience
it can come up with the best function given its computational limitations. So, what is
very important in the designing of a learning algorithm is how to represent the target function
before that what is important is how to represent the training experience. So, the training experience
as we will see can be expressed in the terms of features of the domain and then we have
to decide how to represent the target function. So, we want to come up with the appropriate
class of functions on the features. So, you have to decide the class of the functions and
when we are trying to find this class of the functions we have to make very important decision.
We can go for a very powerful function class which is very complex can represent complex
concepts, but if we choose a powerful rich representation if we choose a rich representation
of the class of functions then we can represent complex function, but and it will be more useful
for subsequent problem solving, but it may be more difficult to learn. So, richer representations
are able to represent many types of classes including complex classes solve complex problems,
but are more difficult to learn and the components of representation as we have said are the
features or the attributes of the domain or the vocabulary on which we define the functions.
So, we have the features and then we have the class of functions which we also call
the hypothesis language. We will talk more about this in the next lecture and when
we in the course of this course as we study different learning algorithms you can keep these
steps in mind. With this we come to the end of introduction. Thank you very much.